Guide to the South Africa Historical Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
South Africa historical collection
1802-1961
MS 1556
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
19.62
(72 boxes)
The collection consists of correspondence; journals and diaries; government documents; reports and printed material of various organizations, political parties, and individuals; ephemera; and photographs which document various aspects of the history of South Africa and its political, economic, social, and cultural conditions from the colonial period of the 1800s to 1948, the year which marks the legalization of apartheid. The bulk of the collection focuses on the South African War, more commonly known as the Boer War (1899-1902).
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred from the African Collection Curator.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Associated Materials
African Collection, MS 605; Pamphlet Collection, MS 1351; African Postcard Collection, MS 1575. Manuscripts and Archives, Yale University Library.
Arrangement
The original accession is arranged chronologically in two categories: manuscript/printed materials and photographs. Additions to collection may vary in arrangement.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of correspondence; journals and diaries; government documents; reports and printed material of various organizations, political parties, and individuals; ephemera; and photographs which document various aspects of the history of South Africa and its political, economic, social, and cultural conditions from the colonial period of the 1800s to 1948, the year which marks the legalization of apartheid. The bulk of the collection focuses on the South African War, more commonly known as the Boer War (1899-1902).
Big game hunting -- South Africa; Diamond mines and mining -- South Africa; Prisoners of War -- South Africa; South African War, 1899-1902 -- Personal narratives; South African War, 1899-1902; Spion Kop, Battle of, South Africa, 1900; Barberton Greenstone Belt (South Africa and Swaziland); Bloemfontein (South Africa); Cape Town (South Africa); Durban (South Africa); Johannesburg (South Africa); Ladysmith (South Africa) -- History -- Siege, 1899-1900; Mafikeng (South Africa) -- History -- Siege, 1899-1900; South Africa -- Description and travel; South Africa -- Economic conditions; South Africa -- History -- 1836-1909; South Africa -- History -- 1909-1961; South Africa -- Politics and government; South Africa -- Social life and customs; Transvaal (South Africa); Lantern slides; Photographs -- South Africa; Jarvis, Weston, 1855-; Nicholl, H. I. (Hugh Iltid), 1870-; Rhodes, Cecil, 1853-1902; Groote Schuur (Cape Town, South Africa); Thomas Cook (Firm); United Party (South Africa)
- Inventory, 1802-1961
  Scope and Contents
  This listing is arranged in chronological order.
  - Manuscripts/printed matter
    - Cape Colony legal documents [papers concerning the Justice Department, the Notary, and real estate], 1802, 1815-1821, 1840 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Letter from British sea captain to Monsieur le Compte d'Escotais of Cape Town [concerning the return of French vessel Sylphe to French authorities], 1819 October 25 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Order of the Privy Council of George IV [approving a rate of exchange in British silver money per paper dollar in the payment of British troops serving in the Cape of Good Hope and Ceylon], 1825 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Bower, John [correspondence and documents concerning Cape farms], 1835-1844 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - "The Journal of William Clayton Humphreys; Being a Personal Narrative of the Adventures and Experiences of a Trader and Hunter in the Zulu Country During the Months of July-October, 1851" [reprinted], 1993 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Russell, Anne Emily A. [manuscript diary describing life in Cape Town], 1852-1853 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - "The Schreiner House, Cradock" [brochure for home/gallery devoted primarily to Olive Schreiner, South Africa's first noted English prose writer (1855-1920)] [published], 1993 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - "The Cape Town-Simon's Town Railway (1860)" [brochure published by the Cape Town Heritage Trust], 1990 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - "125th Anniversary of the Arrival of Indentured Indian Labour to Natal, 1860-1985" [published], 1986 [published] (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Journal/diary of an English? trader [transcriptions included], 1871 July 22-1872 April 15 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Kower, J. P., Jr. [travel journals entitled "From Cleveland to South Africa," "Last Stop at the Diamond Field," "Trip to England," and "Safe in London"], 1872-1874 (Box 1, Folder 11 - 12)
    - Hawes, Alfred [illustrated pocket diary describing trans-Atlantic voyage from Massachusetts to South Africa to acquire native birds and animals], 1874 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Orders in Council of Queen Victoria [regarding annexation of territories and revocation of letters of patent], 1878-1894 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Orders in Council of Queen Victoria and Edward VII [Natal; regarding fugitive colonies, responsible government, native locations], 1878-1907 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Orders in Council of Queen Victoria and Edward VII with the advice of the Privy Council [Basutoland, Bechuanaland, Griqualand West, and Swaziland; regarding annexation, fugitive criminals, administration of justice, appointment of resident commissioners, Crown lands, etc.], 1878-1909 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Hendrie, James H. [letters from South African diamond fields, transcribed by Margaret R. Meyer], 1879-1886 (Box 2, Folder 17 - 19)
    - Fraser, Thomas [copy letters dating from during and after the First Boer War; eyewitness account of the Battle of Majuba Hill], 1881 March 8- October 17 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - "The Salvation Army, South Africa Territory, A Century of Service [1883-1983]" [commemorative centenary booklet] (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Cape Infantry regiment [recruitment poster], 1885 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Mansel-Dakyns, Lort, A Year on Bully Beef and Biscuits or Methuen's Horse in Becuanaland [typescript by a sergeant in C Troop of Methuen's First Mounted Rifles], [1885?] (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - "The Chartered Companies" A Year on Bully Beef and Biscuits or Methuen's Horse in Becuanaland [typescript regarding the Niger Company (1886-1899), the Imperial British East Africa Company (1887-1895); and the British South Africa Company (1889-1923; footnotes], Circa 1981 (Box 2, Folder 24 - 26)
    - "James Stuart's Notes and Queries on John Bird's Annals of Natal," edited by Grant Christison [1888], 1994 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Letter from the postmaster to F. Hanbury Stacy, member of Parliament, concerning the mailing of postcards to countries outside of the Union, 1888 May 17 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Sigcau, Paramount Chief of the Pondo Nation [interview by P. H. Faure, Secretary of Native Affairs], 1891 October (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Ross, David [manuscript diary of a surgeon on the S.S. Ilovo; London to Durham, includes sketches and newspaper clippings], 1897 February 27-May 17 (Box 2, Folder 30 - 31)
    - Land grant certificate of the Zuid-Afrikaansche Republiek (Z. A. R.) [bearing signature of President S. J. P. Kruger], 1897 May 21 (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - Calitzdorp Irrigation Scheme [document of coal specifications and contracts], 1898, undated (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - Reitz, Francis W., State Secretary of the Transvaal and former President of the Orange Free State [notification of the appointment of R. F. Aling as magistrate to Klerksdorp], 1898 July 9 (Box 3, Folder 34)
    - "Souvenir of the Seige of Mafeking" [reproductions of orders issued by General Baden-Powell]; The Mafeking Mail [special siege issue], 1899-1900 (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - Boer War [letters from soldiers], 1899-1903 (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - Frampton, Fred J. [soldier's diary describing journey from England to Bloemfontein; includes impressions of the Boers], 1899 October 6- 1900 March 15 (Box 3, Folder 37)
    - "John Bull in Zuid Afrika" [Dutch anti-British illustrated pamphlet regarding Boer War], [1899-1902?] (Box 3, Folder 38)
    - Ruda, Richard M., "The Irish Nationalist Reaction to the South African War, 1899-1902", 1973 (Box 3, Folder 39 - 41)
    - "Ladysmith and Lydenburg: Anglo-Boer War Letters of Alfred Markham" [1899-1902], 1993 (Box 3, Folder 42)
    - The City of London Imperial Volunteers (C. I. V.) [illustrated souvenir book], 1900 (Box 3, Folder 43)
    - Litchford, R. [notebook written while in prisoner of war camp on St. Helena], 1900 (Box 3, Folder 44)
    - The Morning Leader [leaflets: #5 "The Real Motive for the War" and #7 "The Hawksley Diary"], 1900 (Box 3, Folder 45)
    - Victor, Christian [bills of sale and photographs with biographical information], 1900 (Box 3, Folder 46)
    - "The Siege Valentine" [illustrated card concerning the Siege of Ladysmith], 1900 February 14 (Box 3, Folder 47)
    - National Bazaar in Aid of the Sufferers by the War [souvenir and official program], 1900 (Box 3, Folder 48)
    - Kitchener, Commander in Chief [notice to Burgers in Pretoria recommending their voluntary surrender], 1900 December 20 (Box 3, Folder 49)
    - Ogden's Limited Cigarette Cards "Tab" Series [60 different cards depicting military or political personalities from the Boer War; includes Baden Powell, Churchill, Rhodes, Cronje, and Joubert], 1900 (Box 3, Folder 50)
    - "The Red Cross in the Boer War" [four different chromo lithographed, die-cut scraps], 1900 (Box 3, Folder 51)
    - Carruthers, Jane, "Attitudes to Game Conservation in the Transvaal, 1900-1910" [thesis], 1985 (Box 3, Folder 52)
    - Tobacco and cigarette collectible cards ["African Types" and "Transvaal Series"], Circa 1900 (Box 3, Folder 53)
    - Sullivan, Harry I., [letter describing a campaign in the Orange Free State during the Boer War], 1901 Dec2 (Box 3, Folder 54)
    - Crofton, Henry William George [letters and photographs relating to his death in the Boer War], 1902 Mar, Apr, undated (Box 4, Folder 55)
    - Copies of documents regarding peace negotiations between Lord Kitchener and Generals Botha De Wet and De La Rey, 1902 April 18 (Box 4, Folder 56)
    - The Bloemfontein Post [declaration of peace flyer], 1902 (Box 4, Folder 57)
    - Boer/Afrikaner women and children in South African War [two articles on their plight and treatment], 1902-1905 (Box 4, Folder 58)
    - "Report on the Organization and Working of the South African Permit Office" [prepared by the Intelligence Division, War Office], 1903 (Box 4, Folder 59)
    - Transvaal Consolidated Land and Exploration Co., Limited [report on agriculture], 1903 January 30 (Box 4, Folder 60)
    - Orange River Colony [agreement regarding purchase of lands], 1903 February 18 (Box 4, Folder 61)
    - Chinese labour in the Transvaal [booklets], 1904 (Box 4, Folder 62)
    - Buller, Redvers, Commander in Chief in South Africa who raised the siege of Ladysmith [letters to Captain E. W. Parker regarding publication of their private correspondence], 1904 November (Box 4, Folder 63)
    - Johnston, Colonel D. A. [documents from his estate concerning the government in post-war Transvaal], 1906-1907 (Box 4, Folder 64 - 65)
      General
      See also: Inventory, 1802-1961 Folder 220
    - Central South African Railways [agreement between the Inter-Colonial Council of the Transvaal and Orange River Colony, the Klerksdorp-Fourteen Steams Railway Company, and the De Beers Consolidated Mines Limited for acquisition of the Klerksdorp-Fourteen Streams Railway], 1907 (Box 4, Folder 66)
    - "Letters from South Africa" [journal from unidentified father to son, includes photographs of journey from England; railroads, mines, and landscape], 1907 July-September (Box 4, Folder 67)
    - National Party [South African election results], 1910-1958 (Box 4, Folder 68)
    - "A Christian Colour-Sergeant: Brief Memoir of Col-Sergt. Macmillan" [biography and letters, 3rd ed.], 1912 (Box 4, Folder 69)
    - "The Syndicalist Conspiracy in South Africa" [speech on deportations by General J. C. Smuts, Minister of Defence], 1914 March 3 (Box 4, Folder 70)
    - Letter from the captain of H. M. S. "Albion" in Walfisch Bay, S. W. Africa [reporting his ship's movements between Oct 31 and Nov 15, 1914], 1914 November 16 (Box 4, Folder 71)
    - Kirby, W. H., Hunting the Hun in (British) South West Africa [series of sketches on the humorous side of the German South West African Campaign], [1915?] (Box 4, Folder 72)
    - Letter from Miss Emily, a school teacher of Marilzbury to her cousin Romola in England [personal letter touching briefly on civil uprising], 1915 January 10 (Box 4, Folder 73)
    - The native riots at Port Elizabeth of October 23, 1920 [official report and letter], 1921 (Box 4, Folder 74)
    - Glass, C. F. [member of the South African section of the Communist International, letters to the editor], 1921-1924 (Box 4, Folder 75)
    - Port Elizabeth [travel brochure], Circa 1923 (Box 4, Folder 76)
    - Class Areas Bill [statements by the Indian Deputation and the Natal Indian Association], 1924 (Box 4, Folder 77)
    - Smuts, Jan Christiaan, "Memorandum on Government Natives and Coloured Bills", 1926 (Box 4, Folder 78)
    - Union Education Department [notes on conference and documents regarding native education], 1928, 1933 (Box 4, Folder 79)
    - Maclachlan, A. N. L., "South African Railways: A Short Description of, and Notes on, the System and its Locomotives, Train Services and Characteristics", 1930-1932 (Box 5, Folder 80)
    - Department of Agriculture and Forestry, Veterinary Division [paper on foot and mouth diseases], 1936 (Box 6, Folder 81 - 83)
    - British Commonwealth of Nations [souvenir program of exhibition], 1936 September-1937 January (Box 6, Folder 84)
    - Lindberg, Scott, Native Housing, 1937 (Box 6, Folder 85)
    - Industrial Conciliation Act [regarding the clothing industry in the Transvaal], 1937-1939, 1942-1943, 1946-1948 (Box 6, Folder 86)
    - "Report of the Departmental Committee of Enquiry into the Collection of Native Tax", 1938 February 21 (Box 6, Folder 87)
    - Transvaal Chamber of Mines, "Memorandum on the Mortality Amongst Tropical Natives Employed on the Witwatersrand Gold Mines", 1938 April (Box 6, Folder 88)
    - Hoernle, A. W., "An Appeal to the People of South Africa" [letter objecting to the South African Senate Bill which would deprive blacks of the vote], Circa 1938 (Box 6, Folder 89)
    - South Africa Institute of Race Relations [reports and statements on labor issues, native affairs, and the Indian people], Circa 1938, 1949-1959 (Box 6, Folder 90)
    - Johannesburg District Communist Party, 1939-1940 (Box 6, Folder 91 - 92)
    - United Party [speeches, souvenir books, photographs, including "Letters of a Farmer"; election materials and statements of policy including "What is Nationalist Party Policy for 18 Year Olds and Under?"; program from Congresses], 1939, 1945-1959, undated (Box 6, Folder 93 - 95)
      See also: Inventory, 1802-1961 Folder 101
      See also: Inventory, 1802-1961 Folder 68
    - The German-African Party (Anti-Nazi) (G. A. P.), Fanfare [periodical], 1940 (Box 6, Folder 96)
    - Honikman, A. H., "Racial Amity in City's [Cape Town's] Franchise History," from Coloured Municipal Vote Record, Circa 1940 (Box 6, Folder 97)
    - Ossewabrandwag [loosely translated as ox wagon sentinels, an organization founded in 1938 to preserve culture of South Africa], 1941 (Box 6, Folder 98)
    - Johannesburg riots of January 31 and February 1, 1941 [the official report given by Sir Patrick Duncan, Governor General], 1941 March 19 (Box 6, Folder 99)
    - Coghlan, Mark, "Schrapnel, Sand and Stukas: The Carbineers in the Western Desert, 1941-1942", 1992 (Box 7, Folder 100)
    - The Union of South Africa (Nationalist Party) [statements on foreign and native policy, paper on progress achieved, constitution], 1941-1948 (Box 7, Folder 101)
      See also: Inventory, 1802-1961 Folder 93 - 95
      General note
    - Clutterbuck, N. S. [South African Air Force flight logbook; correspondence and photographs laid in], 1941-1945, 1950 (Box 7, Folder 102)
    - "Clothing Requirements Survey," Industrial Development Corporation of South Africa, Ltd., 1943 (Box 7, Folder 103)
    - Non-European Unity Movement (N. E. U. M) [papers, declarations, and addresses concerning trade unions and congresses], 1943, 1951, 1960 (Box 7, Folder 104)
    - "Prisoners of War Newspapers" [reproductions from "The Benghazi Forum" and "The Tuturano Times"], 1944 (Box 7, Folder 105)
    - "Cape Town Citizens" [booklet of proceedings of group's 49th meetings, includes Cape Town mayor's broadcast on invasion of Europe by Allied troops], 1944 July (Box 7, Folder 106)
    - Army Educational Services, "What the Soldier Thinks" [unpublished, confidential study by the Union Defense Forces], 1945 (Box 7, Folder 107)
    - National Union of South African Students (N. U. S. A. S) [magazine, booklet, letter on academic freedom and university segregation], 1946, 1954-1956 (Box 7, Folder 108)
    - "The Royal Visit" [official souvenir program for visit of King George VI and Queen Elizabeth to Durban and Port Elizabeth], 1947 (Box 7, Folder 109)
    - United Nations General Assembly [evaluation of attempts to implement the December 18, 1946 resolution to end discrimination against Indians in South Africa], [1947?] (Box 7, Folder 110)
    - Setalvad, M. C., leader of Indian Delegation to the United Nations General Assembly [speech on the treatment of Indians in South Africa], 1948 May 9 (Box 7, Folder 111)
    - Die Nuus [newspaper], 1948 May 15 (Box 7, Folder 112)
    - The Civil Rights League [printed material on citizenship, democracy, apartheid and purpose of organization], 1948-1958 (Box 7, Folder 113)
    - Siegfried, Andre, "Les Problèmes Ethniques de L'Afrique du Sud," [conference; Supplèment au Bulletin de l'Association des Anciens Etudiants de l'UniversitèColoniale de Belgique], 1949 February 21 (Box 7, Folder 114)
    - Government Gazette [newspaper of the Union of South Africa], 1950-1957 (Box 7, Folder 115)
    - Transvaal Indian Organization (T. I. O.) [letters, bulletins, congress notes], [1950?]-1958 (Box 7, Folder 116)
    - Hector, A. R. and Calderwood, D. M., "A New Native Town for Witbank Municipality," National Building Research Institute, South African Council for Scientific and Industrial Research, 1951 June (Box 7, Folder 117)
    - The Africa Bureau [pamphlets on labor, native resources, culture, and apartheid], [1951?]-1958 (Box 7, Folder 118)
    - Van Riebeeck Festival [tercentennial commemoration of Jan van Riebeeck's landing at the Cape], 1952 (Box 7, Folder 119)
    - Cilliers, A. C., " Ex Unitate Vires; A Plea for a Grand Political Alliance as a Prerequisite for the Solution of the South African Trilemma", 1952 (Box 8, Folder 120)
    - Die Middellander [newspaper], 1952 May 9 (Box 8, Folder 121)
    - "High Court of Parliament Reverses Appeal Judgment on Voter's Act" [South Africa news cable], 1952 August 28 (Box 8, Folder 122)
    - South African Institute of International Affairs [papers, letters, and addresses on politics, economy, and defense], 1954-1958 (Box 8, Folder 123)
    - Transvaal Indian Youth Congress (T. I. Y. C.) [bulletins and newsletters; programs, speeches, and printed materials from annual conferences], 1954-1961 (Box 8, Folder 124 - 127)
    - The Liberal Party [letters and statements of policy], [1954?]-1956 (Box 8, Folder 128)
    - Brookes, Edgar, The Constitution and Public Confidence [published by Defenders of the Constitution], 1955 July (Box 8, Folder 129)
    - Du Plessis, W. C., chairman of the South African delegation [statement on apartheid to the Ad Hoc Political Committee], 1955 November 9 (Box 8, Folder 130)
    - Hepple, Alex, A Trade Union Guide for South African Workers [published by South African Congress of Trade Unions (SACTU)], 1957 (Box 8, Folder 131)
    - "Administration of the Group Appeals Act" [report by unidentified author], 1957-1958 (Box 8, Folder 132)
    - "Boycott of Nationalist Controlled Products" [pamphlet], 1957 May 28 (Box 8, Folder 133)
    - Opinion [Indian newspaper], 1957 October 11 (Box 8, Folder 134)
    - "The Multi-Racial Conference," [University of the Witwatersrand], 1957 December 3-5 (Box 8, Folder 135)
    - "The Tightrope Dancers" [report of the 7th Annual Conference, Institute of Administrator of Non-European Affairs], 1958 September 30-October 3 (Box 8, Folder 136)
    - Socialist League of Africa (newsletters and editorials], 1958-1961 (Box 8, Folder 137)
    - Society of Young Africa [bulletin], 1959 February (Box 8, Folder 138)
    - "The Bahufutshe of Manyane" [brief history], 1959 August 8 (Box 8, Folder 139)
    - University College of Fort Hare [student magazine and graduation booklet], 1959 October 28 (Box 8, Folder 140)
    - The Progressive Party of South Africa [booklet entitled Franchise Proposals and Constitutional Safeguards ], 1960 (Box 8, Folder 141)
    - "Disturbances in South Africa: Behind the Headlines" [official statement of the South African Government to U.S. News and World Report ], 1960 April 18 (Box 8, Folder 142)
    - South African Conciliation Committee [newsletter, membership card], undated (Box 8, Folder 143)
    - Whither South Africa?: An analysis of Fascism, Nazism and Greyshirtism and their influence on the politics of the Union [published by South African Liberty Press], undated (Box 8, Folder 144)
    - South Africa Rugby Cards ["Play Up De Beers," "Watch Your Men Kimberley," and "Well Done Natal"], undated (Box 8, Folder 145)
    - "The Picture Postcard" [advertisement for Boer War mementoes], undated (Box 8, Folder 146)
    - African Peoples' Democratic Union of Southern Africa (APDUSA), undated (Box 8, Folder 147)
  - Photographs
    - Loose (not in albums)
      - Wilson, George Washington, [ca. 1870-1889] (Box 9, Folder 148)
      - Clarks, E. D., [1878?] (Box 9, Folder 149 - 150)
      - Kimberley diamond mines, 1880s-1890s (Box 9, Folder 151)
      - Cape Town area, 1890 (Box 9, Folder 152)
      - Middlebrook, John Ernest [Zulu and Natal Tribes], 1880s-1890s (Box 9, Folder 153)
      - Rhodes, Cecil John [loose photographs and photograph album taken by an unidentified friend or servant of Rhodes's], Circa 1890 (Box 9, Folder 154)
      - Durban and locality [plate photographs taken by W. H. Caney, J. E. M., and unidentified photographers depicting city center, beach, promenade, park and town hall, Musgrave Road, entrance to Port Natal], 1890s (Box 9, Folder 155)
      - Cape Town, Circa 1897 (Box 9, Folder 156 - 158)
      - Portraits: identified sitters, 1897-1900, undated (Box 9, Folder 159)
      - British troops bound for South Africa, Circa 1900 (Box 9, Folder 160)
      - Boer War: miscellaneous photographs, 1900-1902 (Box 9, Folder 161)
      - Boers in the prisoner of war camp at Shahjahanpur, 1900-1902 (Box 9, Folder 162)
      - Unidentified photographs, 1905 (Box 10, Folder 163)
      - Agricultural show, 1908 (Box 10, Folder 164)
      - East African Campaign, World War I [stereoscopic photographs], [1914-1918] (Box 10, Folder 165)
      - War internment camp: German prisoners of war, Pietermaritzburg, Natal, 1915 (Box 10, Folder 166)
      - Cuthbert's buildings, Port Elizabeth [a boys school?], 1915-1917, undated (Box 10, Folder 167 - 169)
      - Diamond laborers at Kimberley, search of, undated (Box 10, Folder 170)
      - Bridges, dams [dongas?], undated (Box 10, Folder 171)
      - Portraits: unidentified subjects, undated (Box 10, Folder 172)
      - Postcards of places, natives, undated (Box 10, Folder 173)
      - Groote Schuur [residence of Cecil Rhodes], undated (Box 10, Folder 174)
      - Native life in Natal, undated (Box 10, Folder 175)
      - Thanksgiving service, Church Square, Pretoria, undated (Box 10, Folder 176)